<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" IndexingMethod="Automated" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34558044</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>28</Volume><Issue>44</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Escalating SARS-CoV-2 circulation in environment and tracking waste management in South Asia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><MedlinePgn>61951-61968</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-021-16396-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The novel coronavirus disease of 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has caused an exceptional drift of production, utilization, and disposal of personal protective equipment (PPE) and different microplastic objects for safety against the virus. Hence, we reviewed related literature on severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) RNA detected from household, biomedical waste, and sewage to identify possible health risks and status of existing laws, regulations, and policies regarding waste disposal in South Asian (SA) countries. The SARS-CoV-2 RNA was detected in sewage and wastewater samples of Nepal, India, Pakistan, and Bangladesh. Besides, this review reiterates the enormous amounts of PPE and other single-use plastic wastes generated from healthcare facilities and households in the SA region with inappropriate disposal, landfilling, and/or incineration techniques wind-up polluting the environment. Consequently, the Delta variant (B.1.617.2) of SARS-CoV-2 has been detected in sewer treatment plant in India. Moreover, the overuse of non-biodegradable plastics during the pandemic is deteriorating plastic pollution condition and causes a substantial health risk to the terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems. We recommend making necessary adjustments, adopting measures and strategies, and enforcement of the existing biomedical waste management and sanitation-related policy in SA countries. We propose to adopt the knowledge gaps to improve COVID-19-associated waste management and legislation to prevent further environmental pollution. Besides, the citizens should follow proper disposal procedures of COVID-19 waste to control the environmental pollution.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Islam</LastName><ForeName>Ariful</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA. arif@ecohealthalliance.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Integrative Ecology, School of Life and Environmental Science, Deakin University, Burwood, Victoria, 3216, Australia. arif@ecohealthalliance.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kalam</LastName><ForeName>Md Abul</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Helen Keller International, Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sayeed</LastName><ForeName>Md Abu</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shano</LastName><ForeName>Shahanaj</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahman</LastName><ForeName>Md Kaisar</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Islam</LastName><ForeName>Shariful</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferdous</LastName><ForeName>Jinnat</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choudhury</LastName><ForeName>Shusmita Dutta</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>EcoHealth Alliance, New York, NY, 10001-2320, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research (IEDCR), Dhaka, 1212, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassan</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Mahmudul</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Chattogram Veterinary and Animal Sciences University, Chattogram, 4225, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010969">Plastics</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017753" MajorTopicYN="N">Ecosystem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010154" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Pakistan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010969" MajorTopicYN="N">Plastics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018505" MajorTopicYN="Y">Waste Management</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sanitation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">South Asia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Waste management</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>01</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34558044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-16396-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-021-16396-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8459815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Abd El-Salam MM (2010) Hospital waste management in El-Beheira governorate, Egypt. J Env Manag 91:618–629</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd Manaf L, Samah MAA, Zukki NIM (2009) Municipal solid waste management in Malaysia: practices and challenges. Waste Manag 29:2902–2906</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Shafy HI, Mansour MS (2018) Solid waste issue: sources, composition, disposal, recycling, and valorization. Egyptian J Petro 27:1275–1290</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdulla F, Qdais HA, Rabi A (2008) Site investigation on medical waste management practices in northern Jordan. Waste Manag 28:450–458</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ADB (2020) ADB Data Room: managing infectious medical waste during the COVID-19 pandemic. Available at: https://www.adb.org/publications/managing-medical-waste-covid19 . Accessed on 5 May 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adu RO, Gyasi SF, Essumang DK, Otabil KB (2020) Medical waste-sorting and management practices in five hospitals in Ghana. J Env Pub Heal 2020:1–14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Angel N, Edson J, Bibby K, Bivins A, O'Brien JW, Choi PM, Kitajima M, Simpson SL, Li J (2020) First confirmed detection of SARS-CoV-2 in untreated wastewater in Australia: a proof of concept for the wastewater surveillance of COVID-19 in the community. Sci Total Environ 138764</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed F, Islam MA, Kumar M, Hossain M, Bhattacharya P, Islam MT, Hossen F, Hossain MS, Islam MS, Uddin MM (2021) First detection of SARS-CoV-2 genetic material in the vicinity of COVID-19 isolation centre in Bangladesh: variation along the sewer network. Sci Total Environ 776:145724</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam M-U, Sharior F, Ferdous S, Ahsan A, Ahmed T, Afrin A, Sarker S, Akand F, Archie RJ, Hasan K (2020) Strategies to connect low-income communities with the proposed sewerage network of the Dhaka sanitation improvement project, Bangladesh: a qualitative assessment of the perspectives of stakeholders. Int J Environ Res Public Health 17:7201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albastaki A, Naji M, Lootah R, Almeheiri R, Almulla H, Almarri I, Alreyami A, Aden A, Alghafri R (2020) First confirmed detection of SARS-COV-2 in untreated municipal and aircraft wastewater in Dubai, UAE: the use of wastewater based epidemiology as an early warning tool to monitor the prevalence of COVID-19. Sci Total Environ 143350</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali M, Wang W, Chaudhry N (2016) Management of wastes from hospitals: a case study in Pakistan. Waste Manag Res 34:87–90</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali M, Wang W, Chaudhry N, Geng Y (2017) Hospital waste management in developing countries: a mini review. Waste Manag Res 35:581–592</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin MA (2020) Dhaka Tribune; COVID-19: 14,500 tons waste generated, waste collector halved in a month, available at: https://www.dhakatribune.com/bangladesh/2020/05/10/covid-19-14-500-tons-waste-generated-waste-collector-halved-in-a-month . Accessed on 22 Dec 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin N, Rahman M, Raj S, Ali S, Green J, Das S, Doza S, Mondol MH, Wang Y, Islam MA (2019) Quantitative assessment of fecal contamination in multiple environmental sample types in urban communities in Dhaka, Bangladesh using SaniPath microbial approach. PLoS ONE 14:e0221193</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin N, Haque R, Rahman MZ, Rahman MZ, Mahmud Z, Hasan R, Sarker S, Akter N, Johnston D, Rahman M, Bhattacharya P (2021) Hospitals in Dhaka and discharge of wastewater with high SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA genetic loadings: an assessment of potential environmental health risk. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/351111377_Hospitals_in_Dhaka_and_discharge_of_wastewater_with_high_SARS-CoV-2_viral_RNA_genetic_loadings_An_assessment_of_potential_environmental_health_risk . Accessed on 25 June 25 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ananth AP, Prashanthini V, Visvanathan C (2010) Healthcare waste management in Asia. Waste Manag 30:154–161</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aragaw TA (2020) Surgical face masks as a potential source for microplastic pollution in the COVID-19 scenario. Mar Pollut Bull 159:111517</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora S, Nag A, Rajpal A, Tiwari SB, Sethi J, Sutaria D, Rajvanshi J, Saxena S, Shrivastava SK, Kazmi AA (2020a) Detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in fourteen wastewater treatment systems in Uttarakhand and Rajasthan States of North India. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.09.18.20197178</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora S, Nag A, Sethi J, Rajvanshi J, Saxena S, Shrivastava SK, Gupta AB, (2020b) Sewage surveillance for the presence of SARS-CoV-2 genome as a useful wastewater based epidemiology (WBE) tracking tool in India. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.18.20135277</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azharul Haq K (2006) Water management in Dhaka. Water Res Dev 22:291–311</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babu BR, Parande A, Rajalakshmi R, Suriyakala P, Volga M (2009) Management of biomedical waste in India and other countries: a review. J Int Environ Appl Sci 4:65–78</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahauddin K, Uddin M (2012) Prospect of solid waste situation and an approach of environmental management measure (EMM) model for sustainable solid waste management: case study of Dhaka city. J Environ Sci Nat Resour 5:99–111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banik R, Rahman M, Sikder MT, Gozal D (2020)SARS-CoV-2 pandemic: an emerging public health concern for the poorest in Bangladesh. Pub Health Prac 100024:100024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anon (2011) Technical Guidelines on the Environmentally Sound Co-processing of Hazardous Wastes in Cement Kilns. Available at: http://www.basel.int . Accessed on 10 Feb 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behnam B, Oishi SN, Uddin SMN, Rafa N, Nasiruddin SM, Mollah A, Hongzhi M (2020) Inadequacies in hospital waste and sewerage management in Chattogram, Bangladesh: exploring environmental and occupational health hazards. Sustainability 12:9077</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boechat CL, de Santana Arauco AM, Duda RM, de Sena AFS, de Souza MEL, Brito ACC (2017) Solid waste in agricultural soils: an approach based on environmental principles, human health, and food security. Solid Waste Manag Rural Areas 81</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casanova L, Rutala WA, Weber DJ, Sobsey MD (2009) Survival of surrogate coronaviruses in water. Water Res 43:1893–1898</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty P, Pasupuleti M, Jai Shankar MR, Bharat GK, Krishnasamy S, Dasgupta SC, Sarkar SK, Jones KC (2021) First surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 and organic tracers in community wastewater during post lockdown in Chennai, South India: Methods, occurrence and concurrence. Sci Total Environ 778:146252</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chartier Y (2014) Safe management of wastes from health-care activities. World Health Organization. Available at: https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/42175/9241545259.pdf . Accessed on 10 June 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheval S, Mihai Adamescu C, Georgiadis T, Herrnegger M, Piticar A, Legates DR (2020) Observed and potential impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on the environment. Int J Environ Res Public Health 17:4140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chin AWH, Chu JTS, Perera MRA, Hui KPY, Yen HL, Chan MCW, Poon LLM (2020) Stability of SARS-CoV-2 in different environmental conditions. Lancet Microbe 1:e10. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2666-5247(20)30003-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(20)30003-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CNN (2020) Discarded masks and gloves are becoming a health hazard as people dump them on streets. Available at: https://edition.cnn.com/2020/04/21/us/coronavirus-ppe-masks-gloves-environment-hazard-trnd/index.html . Accessed on 10 June 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dana T (2011) Hospital waste management: Bangladesh. OIDA Int J Sustain Dev 2:29–40</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Datta P, Mohi GK, Chander J (2018) Biomedical waste management in India: critical appraisal. J Lab Phys 10:6–014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhokhikah Y, Trihadiningrum Y (2012) Solid waste management in Asian developing countries: challenges and opportunities. J Appl Environ Bio Sci 2:329–335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorji U, Tenzin UM, Dorji P, Wangchuk U, Tshering G, Dorji C, Shon H, Nyarko KB, Phuntsho S (2019) Wastewater management in urban Bhutan: assessing the current practices and challenges. Process Saf Environ Prot 132:82–93</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan SM, Zhao XS, Wen RF, Huang JJ, Pi GH, Zhang SX, Research Team SARS (2003) Stability of SARS coronavirus in human specimens and environment and its sensitivity to heating and UV irradiation. Biomedical and Environmental Sciences: BES 16(3):246–255</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ESDO (2020) ESDO’s online press briefing on COVID-19 pandemic outbreak 14,500 tons of hazardous plastic waste in a month. Available at: https://esdo.org/esdos-online-press-briefing-on-hazardous-plastic-waste-generation-in-a-month-during-covid-19-pandemic . Accessed on 20 Apr 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faisal GM, Hoque MN, Rahman MS, Islam T (2021)Challenges in medical waste management amid COVID-19 pandemic in a megacity Dhaka. Journal of Advanced Biotechnology and Experimental Therapeutics, 4(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng S, Shen C, Xia N, Song W, Fan M, Cowling BJ (2020) Rational use of face masks in the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet Res Med 8:434–436</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferdous MZ, Islam MS, Sikder MT, Mosaddek ASM, Zegarra-Valdivia J, Gozal D (2020) Knowledge, attitude, and practice regarding COVID-19 outbreak in Bangladesh: an online-based cross-sectional study. PLoS ONE 15:e0239254</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferronato N, Torretta V (2019) Waste mismanagement in developing countries:a review of global issues. Int J Environ Res Public Health 16:1060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foladori P, Cutrupi F, Segata N, Manara S, Pinto F, Malpei F, Bruni L, La Rosa G (2020)SARS-CoV-2 from faeces to wastewater treatment: what do we know? A review. Sci Total Environ 743:140444</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerba CP, Betancourt WQ, Kitajima M (2017) How much reduction of virus is needed for recycled water: a continuous changing need for assessment? Water Res 108:25–31</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghinai I, McPherson TD, Hunter JC, Kirking HL, Christiansen D, Joshi K, Rubin R, Morales-Estrada S, Black SR, Pacilli M (2020) First known person-to-person transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in the USA. Lancet 395:1137–1144</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GISAID (2021) GISAID, Available at: https://www.gisaid.org . Accessed on 21 June 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh GK-M, Dunker AK, Foster JA, Uversky VN (2020) Shell disorder analysis predicts greater resilience of the SARS-CoV-2(COVID-19) outside the body and in body fluids. Micro Path 104177:104177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gundy PM, Gerba CP, Pepper IL (2009) Survival of coronaviruses in water and wastewater. Food Environ Viro 1:10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta PK, Shree V, Hiremath L, Rajendran S (2019) The use of modern technology in smart waste management and recycling: artificial intelligence and machine learning, Recent Advances in Computational Intelligence. Springer, Champ, pp 173–188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gwenzi W (2020) Leaving no stone unturned in light of the COVID-19 faecal-oral hypothesis? A water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH) perspective targeting low-income countries. Sci Total Environ:141751</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque MS, Uddin S, Sayem SM, Mohib KM (2020) Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) induced waste scenario: a short overview. J Environ Chem Engin 104660</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque MS, Sharif S, Masnoon A, Rashid EJWM (2021a) Research, SARS-CoV-2pandemic-induced PPE and single-use plastic waste generation scenario. Waste Manag. Res. 0734242X20980828</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haque, R., Rahman, M., Amin, N., Rahman, M.Z., Mahmud, Z.H., Sarker, P., Raqib, R., Rahman, M.Z.R., Hossain, A., Johnston, D., 2021b. Inference and forecasting of SARS-CoV-2 wastewater surveillance in Bangladesh, CUGH 2021 Virtual Conference. CUGH</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haramoto E, Malla B, Thakali O, Kitajima M (2020) First environmental surveillance for the presence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater and river water in Japan. medRxiv</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harhay MO, Halpern SD, Harhay JS, Olliaro PL (2009) Health care waste management: a neglected and growing public health problem worldwide. Trop Med Int Health 14:1414–1417</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan M, Iqbal SS (2016) Solid waste management of Dhaka South City Corporation (DSCC). J Environ Treat Technol 4:78–10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan MK, Shahriar A, Jim KU (2019) Water pollution in Bangladesh and its impact on public health. Heliyon 5:e02145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan MM, Ahmed SA, Rahman KA, Biswas TK (2008) Pattern of medical waste management: existing scenario in Dhaka City, Bangladesh. BMC Public Health 8:36</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan MM, El Zowalaty ME, Khan SA, Islam A, Nayem MRK, Järhult JD (2020) Role of environmental temperature on the attack rate and case fatality rate of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Pandemic. Inf Eco Epid 10:1792620</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hemalatha M, Kiran U, Kuncha SK, Kopperi H, Gokulan CG, Mohan SV, Mishra RK (2021) Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 spread using wastewater-based epidemiology: comprehensive study. Sci Total Environ. 768:144704</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idris A, Inanc B, Hassan MN (2004) Overview of waste disposal and landfills/dumps in Asian countries. J Mater Cycles Waste Manag 6:104–110</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IGES (2020) Waste management during the COVID-19 pandemic from response to recovery, availabe at: https://www.unenvironment.org/resources/report/waste-management-during-covid-19-pandemic-response-recovery . Accessed on 27 Dec 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iliyas M (2008) Disposal of Waste. Eds.: Iliyas M, Shah KS. Public Health Commu Med. 7th edition. Karachi: Time Publisher, 261-273</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilyas S, Srivastava RR, Kim H (2020) Disinfection technology and strategies for COVID-19 hospital and bio-medical waste management. Sci Total Environ 749:141652</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam T, Kibria MG (2020) Challenges to the prevention of COVID-19 spread in slums of Bangladesh. J Public Health. Oxford, England 40(3); 637-638 </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam A, Sayeed MA, Rahman MK, Ferdous J, Shano S, Choudhury SD, Hassan MM (2020) Spatiotemporal patterns and trends of community transmission of the pandemic COVID-19 in South Asia: Bangladesh as a case study. Bio Health 3(1):39–49</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam A, Sayeed M, Kalam M, Ferdous J, Rahman M, Abedin J, Islam, S., Shano, S., Saha, O., Shirin, T., (2021a) Molecular epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 in diverse environmental samples globally. Microorganisms 9(8):1696</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam A, Sayeed MA, Rahman MK, Ferdous J, Islam S, Hassan M (2021b) Geospatial dynamics of COVID-19 clusters and hotspots in Bangladesh. Transbound Emerg Dis:1–15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, S.M.D., Mondal, P.K., Ojong, N., Bodrud-Doza, M., 2021c. Water, sanitation, hygiene and waste disposal practices as COVID-19 response strategy: insights from Bangladesh. J Env Dev Sustain, 1-22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jui UM (2020) A worrying spike in hazardous plastic waste during the pandemic, available at: https://tbsnews.net/panorama/worrying-spike-hazardous-plastic-waste-during-pandemic-82606 . Accessed on 1 Feb 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kam K-q, Yung CF, Cui L, Tzer Pin Lin R, Mak TM, Maiwald M, Li J, Chong CY, Nadua K, Tan NWH (2020) A well infant with coronavirus disease 2019 with high viral load. Clinical Inf Dis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamal A, Goyer K, Koottatep T, Amin A (2008) Domestic wastewater management in South and Southeast Asia: the potential benefits of a decentralised approach. Urban Water J 5:345–354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kataki S, Chatterjee S, Vairale MG, Sharma S, Dwivedi SK (2020) Concerns and strategies for wastewater treatment during COVID-19 pandemic to stop plausible transmission. Res Con Recy 105156:105156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerdsuwan S, Laohalidanond K (2015) Efficiency improvement for medical waste management. Handbook of Clean Energy Systems:1–11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan AA, Ahmed Z, Siddiqui MA (2012) Issues with solid waste management in South Asian countries: a situational analysis of Pakistan. J Environ Occup Health 1:129–131</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitajima M, Ahmed W, Bibby K, Carducci A, Gerba CP, Hamilton KA, Haramoto E, Rose JB (2020)SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater: state of the knowledge and research needs. Sci Total Environ 139076:139076</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kojima M, Iwasaki F, Johannes HP, Edita EP (2020) Strengthening waste management policies to mitigate the COVID-19 pandemic</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Smith SR, Fowler G, Velis C, Kumar SJ, Arya S, Rena K, Cheeseman RC (2017) Challenges and opportunities associated with waste management in India. Royal Soc Open Sci 4:160764</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Patel AK, Shah AV, Raval J, Rajpara N, Joshi M, Joshi CG (2020a) First proof of the capability of wastewater surveillance for COVID-19 in India through detection of genetic material of SARS-CoV-2. Sci Total Environ 746:141326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar M, Patel AK, Shah AV, Raval J, Rajpara N, Joshi M, Joshi C.G.J.S.o.T.T.E., (2020d) First proof of the capability of wastewater surveillance for COVID-19 in India through detection of genetic material of SARS-CoV-2. 746, 141326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeChevallier MW, Mansfield TJ, Gibson JM (2020) Protecting wastewater workers from disease risks: personal protective equipment guidelines. Wat Env Res 92:524–533</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesimple A, Jasim SY, Johnson DJ, Hilal N (2020) The role of wastewater treatment plants as tools for SARS-CoV-2 early detection and removal. J Wat Pro Eng, 101544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo IL, Lio CF, Cheong HH, Lei CI, Cheong TH, Zhong X, Tian Y, Sin NN (2020) Evaluation of SARS-CoV-2 RNA shedding in clinical specimens and clinical characteristics of 10 patients with COVID-19 in Macau. Int J Bio Sci 16:1698–1707</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmood S, ud Din N, Mohsin J, Javed H (2011) Practices regarding hospital waste management at public and private sector hospitals of Lahore. Annals of King Edward Med Univ 17:113–113</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandal P, Gupta AK, Dubey BK (2020) A review on presence, survival, disinfection/removal methods of coronavirus in wastewater and progress of wastewater-based epidemiology. J Environ Chem Eng:104317</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour G, Islam W, Akhtaruzzaman M (2017) Situation analysis of the urban sanitation sector in Bangladesh. Available at: https://www.aguaconsult.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/Situation-analysis-of-the-urban-sanitation-sector-in-Bangladesh.pdf . Accessed on 10 May 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medema G, Heijnen L, Elsinga G, Italiaander R, Brouwer A (2020) Presence of SARS-coronavirus-2 RNA in sewage and correlation with reported COVID-19 prevalence in the early stage of the epidemic in the Netherlands. Environ Sci Technol Lett 7(7):511–516</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohankumar S, Kottaiveeran K (2011) Hospital waste management and environmental problems in India. Int J Pharma Bio Arch 2(6):1621–1626</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohee R (2005) Medical wastes characterisation in healthcare institutions in Mauritius. Waste Manag 25:575–581</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MOHFW (2008) The medical waste management rules, 2008; availabe at: http://www.clcbd.org/document/133.html . Accessed 23 Dec 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Napit R, Manandhar P, Chaudhary A, Shrestha, B., Poudel, A., Raut, R., Pradhan, S., Raut, S., Mathema, S., Rajbhandari R (2021) Rapid genomic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 in a dense urban community using environmental (sewage) samples. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.03.29.21254053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasrin F (2016) Waste management in Bangladesh: current situation and suggestions for action. Int Res J Soc Sci 5:36–42</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nghiem LD, Morgan B, Donner E, Short MD (2020) The COVID-19 pandemic: considerations for the waste and wastewater services sector. Case Studies Chem Environ Eng 100006:100006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nzediegwu C, Chang SX (2020) Improper solid waste management increases potential for COVID-19 spread in developing countries. Res Con Recy 161:104947</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouhsine O, Ouigmane A, Layati E, Aba B, Isaifan R, Berkani M (2020) Impact of COVID-19 on the qualitative and quantitative aspect of household solid waste. Global J Environ Sci Manage 6:41–52</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey D, Verma S, Verma P, Mahanty B, Dutta K, Daverey A, Arunachalam K (2020)SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater: challenges for developing countries. Int J Hygiene Environ Health 113634:113634</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peccia J, Zulli A, Brackney DE, Grubaugh, N.D., Kaplan, E.H., Casanovas-Massana, A., Ko, A.I., Malik, A.A., Wang, D., Wang, M.J.m (2020) SARS-CoV-2 RNA concentrations in primary municipal sewage sludge as a leading indicator of COVID-19 outbreak dynamics. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.05.19.20105999</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penteado CSG, de Castro MAS (2020)Covid-19 effects on municipal solid waste management: what can effectively be done in the Brazilian scenario? Res Con Recy 164:105152</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu G, Li X, Hu L, Jiang G (2020) An imperative need for research on the role of environmental factors in transmission of novel coronavirus (COVID-19). ACS Publications</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quilliam RS, Weidmann M, Moresco V, Purshouse H, O'Hara Z, Oliver DM (2020) COVID-19: the environmental implications of shedding SARS-CoV-2 in human faeces. Environ Int 140:105790</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabenau HF, Cinatl J, Morgenstern B, Bauer G, Preiser W, Doerr HW (2005) Stability and inactivation of SARS coronavirus. Med Microbiol Immunol 194(1–2):1–6. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00430-004-0219-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00430-004-0219-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ragaert P, Verbeke W, Devlieghere F, Debevere, J.J.F.q., preference (2004) Consumer perception and choice of minimally processed vegetables and packaged fruits 15:259–270</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman MH, Akter R, Behl T, Chowdhur, MA, Mohammed M, Bulbul IJ, Elshenawy SE, Kamal M.AJCPD (2020a)COVID-19 outbreak and emerging management through pharmaceutical therapeutic strategy 26:5224–5240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman MM, Bodrud-Doza M, Griffiths MD, Mamun MA (2020b) Biomedical waste amid COVID-19: perspectives from Bangladesh. Lancet, Global Health</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randazzo W, Truchado P, Cuevas-Ferrand E, Simón, P., Allende, A., Sánchez, G (2020a)SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater anticipated COVID-19 occurrence in a low prevalence area. Water Res, 115942.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randazzo W, Truchado P, Cuevas-Ferrando E, Simón P, Allende A, Sánchez GJ (2020b)SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater anticipated COVID-19 occurrence in a low prevalence area. Wat Res 181:115942</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray A (2008) Waste management in developing Asia: can trade and cooperation help? J Environ Dev 17:3–25</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rimoldi SG, Stefani, F., Gigantiello, A., Polesello, S., Comandatore, F., Mileto, D., Maresca, M., Longobardi, C., Mancon, A., Romeri, F.J.S.o.t.T.E (2020) Presence and infectivity of SARS-CoV-2 virus in wastewaters and rivers 744:140911</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rume, T., Islam, S.D.-U., 2020. Environmental effects of COVID-19 pandemic and potential strategies of sustainability. Heliyon, e04965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saadat S, Rawtani D, Hussain CM (2020) Environmental perspective of COVID-19. Sci Total Environ 138870:138870</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangkham S (2020) Face mask and medical waste disposal during the novel COVID-19 pandemic in Asia. Case Studies Chem Environ Eng 100052:100052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sembiring E, Nitivattananon V (2010) Sustainable solid waste management toward an inclusive society: integration of the informal sector. Res, Con Recy 54:802–809</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shammi M, Tareq SM (2020) Environmental catastrophe of COVID-19: disposal and management of PPE in Bangladesh. Global Soc Wel 8:1–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shammi M, Behal A, Tareq SM (2020) The escalating biomedical waste management to control the environmental transmission of COVID-19 pandemic: a perspective from two South Asian countries. Env Sci Tech 55(7):4087–4093</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharif S, Ikram A, Khurshid A., Salman, M., Mehmood, N., Arshad, Y., Ahmad, J., Angez, M., Alam, M.M., Rehman L 2020. Detection of SARS-coronavirus-2 in wastewater, using the existing environmental surveillance network: an epidemiological gateway to an early warning for COVID-19 in communities. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.03.20121426</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma HB, Vanapalli KR, Cheela VS, Ranjan VP, Jaglan AK, Dubey B, Goel S, Bhattacharya J (2020) Challenges, opportunities, and innovations for effective solid waste management during and post COVID-19 pandemic. Res, Con Recy 162:105052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S, Batra S, Gupta S, Sharma VK, Rahman MH, Kamal MA (2021) Persons with co-existing neurological disorders: risk analysis, considerations and management in COVID-19 pandemic. CNS  Neuro Dis Drug Targets. https://doi.org/10.2174/1871527320666210308113457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmin, A., 2016. Water and wastewater in Bangladesh, current status and a design of a decentralized solution</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheheli S (2007) Waste disposal and management system in rural areas of mymensingh. Progr Agri 18:241–246</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shekdar AV (2009) Sustainable solid waste management: an integrated approach for Asian countries. Waste Manag 29:1438–1448</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair RG, Choi CY, Riley MR, Gerba CP (2008) Pathogen surveillance through monitoring of sewer systems. Adv Appl Micro 65:249</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N, Tang Y, Ogunseitan OA (2020a) Environmentally sustainable management of used personal protective equipment. Environ Sci Tech 54:8500–8502</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N, Tang Y, Zhang Z, Zheng C (2020b)COVID-19 waste management: effective and successful measures in Wuhan, China. Res Con Recy 163:105071</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sizun J, Yu MW, Talbot PJ (2000) Survival of human coronaviruses 229E and OC43 in suspension and after drying onsurfaces: a possible source ofhospital-acquired infections. J Hosp Infect 46:55–60</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Somani M, Srivastava AN, Gummadivalli SK, Sharma A (2020) Indirect implications of COVID-19 towards sustainable environment: an investigation in Indian context. Biores Tech Rep 11:100491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunkari ED, Korboe HM, Abu M, Kizildeniz T (2020) Sources and routes of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in water systems in Africa: are there any sustainable remedies? Sci Total Environ 142298:142298</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed EH, Mutahara M, Rahman M (2012) Medical waste management (MWM) in Dhaka, Bangladesh: it’sa review. Home Health Care Manag Pract 24:140–145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tajmim T (2020) Dengue threat rises amid Covid-19. Available at: https://tbsnews.net/bangladesh/health/dengue-threat-rises-amid-covid-19-111973 . Accessed on 1 Feb 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur V, Ramesh A (2015) Healthcare waste management research: a structured analysis and review (2005–2014). Waste Manag Res 33:855–870</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson RC, Moore CJ, Vom Saal FS, Swan SH (2009) Plastics, the environment and human health: current consensus and future trends. Philos Trans R Soc B Biol Sci 364:2153–2166</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivedi M, Mathur M, Johri P, Singh A, Tiwari RK (2020) Waste management: a paradigm shift, environmental concerns and sustainable development. Springer, pp 337–363</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tudor T, Noonan C, Jenkin L (2005) Healthcare waste management: a case study from the National Health Service in Cornwall, United Kingdom. Waste Manag 25:606–615</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unicef (2020) Water, sanitation and hygiene. Available at: https://www.unicef.org/bangladesh/en . Accessed on 22 Dec 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Doremalen N, Bushmaker T, Morris DH, Holbrook MG, Gamble A, Williamson BN, Tamin A, Harcourt JL, Thornburg NJ, Gerber SI (2020) Aerosol and surface stability of SARS-CoV-2 as compared with SARS-CoV-1. New England J Med 382:1564–1567</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang XW, Li JS, Jin M, Zhen B, Kong QX, Song N, Xiao WJ, Yin J, Wei W, Wang GJ, Si BY, Guo BZ, Liu C, Ou GR, Wang MN, Fang TY, Chao FH, Li JW (2005) Study on the resistance of severe acute respiratory syndrome-associated coronavirus. J Virol Methods 126:171–177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warnes SL, Little ZR, Keevil CW (2015) Human coronavirus 229E remains infectious on common touch surface materials. MBio 6(6):e01697–ee1715. https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01697-15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.01697-15</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WaterAid (2019) Faecal Sludge Management Landscape in South Asia. Available at: https://washmatters.wateraid.org . Accessed on 10 June 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2005a) Management of solid health-care waste at primary health-care centres: a decision-making guide. Available at: https://www.who.int . Accessed on 2 Apr 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2005b) Management of solid health-care waste at primary health-care centres: a decision-making guide, Availabe at: https://www.who.int/water_sanitation_health/medicalwaste/en/guidancemanual1.pdf . Accessed on 22 Dec 2020. WHO Document Production Services, Geneva, Switzerland</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2018)Health-care waste. Available at: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/health-care-waste . Accessed on 28 Jan 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2020) Joint monitoring programme (JMP), WHO, UNICEF. Available at: https://washdata.org/data . Accessed on 22 Dec 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wölfel R, Corman VM, Guggemos W, Seilmaier M, Zange S, Müller MA, Niemeyer D, Jones TC, Vollmar P, Rothe C (2020) Virological assessment of hospitalized patients with COVID-2019. Nature 581:465–469</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong G, Bi Y-H, Wang Q-H, Chen X-W, Zhang Z-G, Yao Y-G(2020) Zoonotic origins of human coronavirus 2019 (HCoV-19/SARS-CoV-2): why is this work important? Zool Res 41:213–219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worldometer (2021) Coronavirus, Available at: https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus . Accessed 25 June 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Xiao A, Zhang J, Moniz K, Endo N, Armas F., Bonneau, R., Brown MA, Bushman, M., Chai P (2020a)SARS-CoV-2 titers in wastewater foreshadow dynamics and clinical presentation of new COVID-19 cases. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.15.20117747</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Guo C, Tang L, Hong Z, Zhou J, Dong X, Yin H, Xiao Q, Tang Y, Qu X (2020b) Prolonged presence of SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA in faecal samples. Lancet Gastro Hepa 5:434–435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wurtzer, S., Marechal, V., Mouchel, J., Maday, Y., Teyssou, R., Richard, E., Almayrac, J., Moulin, L.J.E., 2020. Evaluation of lockdown effect on SARS-CoV-2 dynamics through viral genome quantification in waste water, Greater Paris, France, 5 March to 23 April 2020. 25, 2000776.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao F, Tang M, Zheng X, Liu Y, Li X, Shan H (2020) Evidence for gastrointestinal infection of SARS-CoV-2. Gastroenterology 158:1831–1833</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu S, Li Y (2020) Beware of the second wave of COVID-19. The Lancet 395:1321–1322</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu B, Kraemer MU, Gutierrez B, Mekaru S, Sewalk K, Loskill A, Wang L, Cohn E, Hill S, Zarebski A (2020a) Open access epidemiological data from the COVID-19 outbreak. Lancet Infect Dis 20:534</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Li X, Zhu B, Liang H, Fang C, Gong Y, Guo Q, Sun X, Zhao D, Shen J (2020b) Characteristics of pediatric SARS-CoV-2 infection and potential evidence for persistent fecal viral shedding. Nat Med 26:502–505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaqub T, Nawaz, M., Shabbir, M.Z., Ali, M.A., Altaf, I., Raza, S., Shabbir, M.A.B., Ashraf, M.A., Aziz, S.Z., Cheema SQ (2020) A longitudinal survey for genome-based identification of SARS-CoV-2 in sewage water in selected lockdown areas of Lahore city, Pakistan; a potential approach for future smart lockdown strategy. medRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.07.31.20165126</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasmin S, Rahman MI (2017) A review of solid waste management practice in Dhaka City, Bangladesh. Int Journal Environ Prot Pol 5:19–25</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Sun X, Solvang WD, Zhao X (2020) Reverse logistics network design for effective management of medical waste in epidemic outbreaks: insights from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in Wuhan (China). International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 17:1770</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamparas M, Kapsalis V, Kyriakopoulos G, Aravossis K, Kanteraki A, Vantarakis A, Kalavrouziotis I (2019) Medical waste management and environmental assessment in the Rio University Hospital, Western Greece. Sustain Chem Pharm 13:100163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D, Ling H, Huang X, Li J, Li W, Yi C, Zhang T, Jiang Y, He Y, Deng S (2020) Potential spreading risks and disinfection challenges of medical wastewater by the presence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) viral RNA in septic tanks of Fangcang hospital. Sci Total Environ 741:140445</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>