<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34821383</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association of polymorphisms in tumor necrosis factors with SARS-CoV-2 infection and mortality rate: A case-control study and in silico analyses.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.27477</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The present coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is spreading rapidly and existing data has suggested a number of susceptibility factors for developing a severe course of the disease.  The current case-control experiment is aimed to study the associations of genetic polymorphisms in tumor necrosis factors (TNFs) with COVID-19 and its mortality rate. A total of 550 participants (275 subjects and 275 controls) were enrolled. The tetra-amplification refractory mutation system polymerase chain reaction technique was recruited to detect -308G&gt;A TNFα and +252A&gt;G TNFβ polymorphisms among the Iranian subjects. We demonstrated that carriers of the G allele of TNFβ-252A/G, rs909253 A&gt;G were more frequent in COVID-19 subjects compared to the healthy group and this allele statistically increased the disease risk (odds ratio [OR] = 1.55, 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.23-1.96, p &lt; 0.0001). At the same time, the A allele of TNFα-311A/G, rs1800629 G&gt;A moderately decreased the risk of COVID-19 (OR = 0.68, 95% CI = 0.53-0.86, p &lt; 0.002). Also, we analyzed the various genotypes regarding the para-clinical and disorder severity; we found that in the AA genotype of TNFβ-252A/G (rs909253 A&gt;G), the computed tomography scan pattern was different in comparison to cases carrying the AG genotype with p<sub>1</sub>  &lt; 0.001. In addition, in the severe cases of COVID-19, leukocyte and neutrophil count and duration of intensive care unit hospitalization in the deceased patients were significantly increased (p &lt; 0.001). Moreover, the TNFα-311A/G (rs1800629 G&gt;A) variant is likely to change the pattern of splicing factor sites. Our findings provided deep insights into the relationship between TNFα/TNFβ polymorphisms and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2. Replicated studies may give scientific evidence for exploring molecular mechanisms of COVID-19 in other ethnicities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heidari Nia</LastName><ForeName>Milad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rokni</LastName><ForeName>Mohsen</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0534-4251</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, School of Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Immunology, University of Social Welfare and Rehabilitation Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mirinejad</LastName><ForeName>Shekoufeh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kargar</LastName><ForeName>Maryam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Hematology and Blood Bank, School of Allied Medical Science Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahdar</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sargazi</LastName><ForeName>Saman</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2255-5977</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarhadi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saravani</LastName><ForeName>Ramin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cellular and Molecular Research Center, Research Institute of Cellular and Molecular Sciences in Infectious Diseases, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, School of Medicine Zahedan University of Medical Sciences, Zahedan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Zahedan University of Medical Sciences</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CT pattern</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polymorphism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tumor necrosis factor</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34821383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Srivastava A, Bandopadhyay A, Das D, et al. Genetic association of ACE2 rs2285666 polymorphism with Covid-19 spatial distribution in India. Front Genet. 2020;11:1163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivasankarapillai VS, Pillai AM, Rahdar A, et al. On facing the SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) with combination of nanomaterials and medicine: possible strategies and first challenges. Nanomaterials. 2020;10(5):852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheervalilou R, Shirvaliloo M, Dadashzadeh N, et al. COVID-19 under spotlight: a close look at the origin, transmission, diagnosis, and treatment of the 2019-nCoV disease. J Cell Physiol. 2020;235(12):8873-8924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohrabi C, Alsafi Z, O'neill N, et al. World Health Organization declares global emergency: a review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19). Int J Surg. 2020;76:71-76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sargazi S, Sheervalilou R, Rokni M, Shirvaliloo M, Shahraki O, Rezaei N. The role of autophagy in controlling SARS-CoV-2 infection: an overview on virophagy-mediated molecular drug targets. Cell Biol Int, 45:1599-1612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell F, Archer B, Laurenson-Schafer H, et al. Increased transmissibility and global spread of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern as at June 2021. Euro Surveill. 2021;26(24):2100509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikpouraghdam M, Jalali Farahani A, Alishiri G, et al. Epidemiological characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients in IRAN: a single center study. J Clin Virol. 2020;127:104378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shirvaliloo M, Sheervalilou R. Potential effectiveness of bromhexine hydrochloride as an affordable over-the-counter drug for prophylaxis against COVID-19 in developing countries. Authorea. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirano T, Murakami M. COVID-19: a new virus, but a familiar receptor and cytokine release syndrome. Immunity. 2020;52(5):731-733.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukassen S, Chua RL, Trefzer T, et al. SARS-CoV-2 receptor ACE 2 and TMPRSS 2 are primarily expressed in bronchial transient secretory cells. EMBO J. 2020;39(10):e105114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan C, Yao Y-F, Yang X-L, et al. Infection with novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) causes pneumonia in Rhesus macaques. Cell Res. 2020;30(8):670-677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badellino H, Gobbo ME, Torres E, Aschieri ME. Early indicators and risk factors associated with mental health problems during COVID-19 quarantine: is there a relationship with the number of confirmed cases and deaths? Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2020;67:567-575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim Y-C, Jeong B-H. Strong correlation between the case fatality rate of COVID-19 and the rs6598045 single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) of the interferon-induced transmembrane protein 3 (IFITM3) gene at the population-level. Genes. 2021;12(1):42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vankadari N. Overwhelming mutations or SNPs of SARS-CoV-2: a point of caution. Gene. 2020;752:144792.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paniri A, Hosseini MM, Moballegh-Eslam M, Akhavan-Niaki H. Comprehensive in silico identification of impacts of ACE2 SNPs on COVID-19 susceptibility in different populations. Gene Rep. 2021;22:100979.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleh A, Sultan A, Elashry MA, et al. Association of TNF-α G-308 a promoter polymorphism with the course and outcome of COVID-19 patients. Immunol Invest. 2020:5:1-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chong WP, Ip WE, Tso GHW, et al. The interferon gamma gene polymorphism +874 A/T is associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome. BMC Infect Dis. 2006;6:82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokni M, Hamblin MR. Rezaei N. Cytokines and COVID-19: friends or foes? Hum Vaccines Immunother. 2020;16(10):2363-2365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokni M, Ghasemi V, Tavakoli Z. Immune responses and pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 during an outbreak in Iran: comparison with SARS and MERS. Rev Med Virol. 2020;30(3):e2107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirtipal N, Bharadwaj S. Interleukin 6 polymorphisms as an indicator of COVID-19 severity in humans. J Biomol Struct Dyn. 2021;39:4563-4565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ovsyannikova IG, Haralambieva IH, Crooke SN, Poland GA, Kennedy RB. The role of host genetics in the immune response to SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 susceptibility and severity. Immunol Rev. 2020;296(1):205-219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokni M, Salimi S, Sohrabi T, Asghari S, Teimoori B, Saravani M. Association between miRNA-152 polymorphism and risk of preeclampsia susceptibility. Arch Gynecol Obstet. 2019;299(2):475-480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piva F, Giulietti M, Burini AB, Principato G. SpliceAid 2: a database of human splicing factors expression data and RNA target motifs. Hum Mutat. 2012;33(1):81-85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crooks GE, Hon G, Chandonia J-M, Brenner SE. WebLogo: a sequence logo generator. Genome Res. 2004;14(6):1188-1190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastassopoulou C, Gkizarioti Z, Patrinos GP, Tsakris A. Human genetic factors associated with susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19 disease severity. Hum Genomics. 2020;14:40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokni M, Ahmadikia K, Asghari S, Mashaei S, Hassanali F. Comparison of clinical, para-clinical and laboratory findings in survived and deceased patients with COVID-19: diagnostic role of inflammatory indications in determining the severity of illness. BMC Infect Dis. 2020;20(1):869.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devaux CA, Rolain J-M, Raoult D. ACE2 receptor polymorphism: susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2, hypertension, multi-organ failure, and COVID-19 disease outcome. J Microbiol Immunol Infect. 2020;53(3):425-435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karst M, Hollenhorst J, Achenbach J. Life-threatening course in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): Is there a link to methylenetetrahydrofolic acid reductase (MTHFR) polymorphism and hyperhomocysteinemia? Med Hypotheses. 2020;144:110234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torre-Fuentes L, Matías-Guiu J, Hernández-Lorenzo L, et al. ACE2, TMPRSS2, and Furin variants and SARS-CoV-2 infection in Madrid, Spain. J Med Virol. 2021;93(2):863-869.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stawiski EW, Diwanji D, Suryamohan K, et al. Human ACE2 receptor polymorphisms predict SARS-CoV-2 susceptibility. Communications Biology. 2021;4(1):475.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roszak A, Misztal M, Sowińska A, Jagodziński PP. TNF-α-308 G/A as a risk marker of cervical cancer progression in the Polish population. Mol Diagn Ther. 2015;19(1):53-57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agliardi C, Guerini FR, Zanzottera M, et al. TNF-α-308 G/A and -238 G/A promoter polymorphisms and sporadic Parkinson's disease in an Italian cohort. J Neurol Sci. 2018;385:45-48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz-Valle JF, Oregón-Romero E, Rangel-Villalobos H, et al. High expression of TNF alpha is associated with -308 and -238 TNF alpha polymorphisms in knee osteoarthritis. Clin Exp Med. 2014;14(1):61-67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Cui X, Ning L, Wei D. The effects of tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) rs1800629 and rs361525 polymorphisms on sepsis risk. Oncotarget. 2017;8(67):111456-111469.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tharwat E, Gad G, Nazmy MH, et al. Impact of IL-27p28 (rs153109) and TNF-α (rs1800629) genetic polymorphisms on the progression of HCV infection in Egyptian patients. Immunol Invest. 2019;48(3):255-267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang G, Chen J, Xu F, Bao Z, Yao Y, Zhou J. Association between tumor necrosis factor-α rs1800629 polymorphism and risk of asthma: a meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2014;9(6):e99962.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rutigliano JA, Graham BS. Prolonged production of TNF-α exacerbates illness during respiratory syncytial virus infection. J Immunol. 2004;173(5):3408-3417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding Y, Feng Q, Chen J, Song J. TLR4/NF-κB signaling pathway gene single nucleotide polymorphisms alter gene expression levels and affect ARDS occurrence and prognosis outcomes. Medicine. 2019;98(26):16029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez-Ocaña J, Olivo-Diaz A, Salazar-Dominguez T, et al. Plasma cytokine levels and cytokine gene polymorphisms in Mexican patients during the influenza pandemic A (H1N1) pdm09. J Clin Virol. 2013;58(1):108-113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Wei M, Han Y, et al. Roles of TNF-α gene polymorphisms in the occurrence and progress of SARS-Cov infection: a case-control study. BMC Infect Dis. 2008;8:27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahmer MK, Quasney MW. Genetic polymorphisms in critical illness and injury. Pediatric Critical Care Medicine. Springer; 2014:177-202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neta R, Sayers T, Oppenheim J. Relationship of TNF to interleukins. Immunol Ser. 1992;56:499-566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leija-Martínez JJ, Huang F, Del-Río-Navarro BE, et al. IL-17A and TNF-α as potential biomarkers for acute respiratory distress syndrome and mortality in patients with obesity and COVID-19. Med Hypotheses. 2020;144:109935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karki R, Sharma BR, Tuladhar S, et al. COVID-19 cytokines and the hyperactive immune response: synergism of TNF-α and IFN-γ in triggering inflammation, tissue damage, and death. BioRxiv. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallelli L, Zhang L, Wang T, Fu F. Severe acute lung injury related to COVID-19 infection: a review and the possible role for escin. J Clin Pharmacol. 2020;60(7):815-825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Huang S, Yin L. The cytokine storm and COVID-19. J Med Virol. 2021;93(1):250-256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarzi-Puttini P, Giorgi V, Sirotti S, et al. COVID-19, cytokines and immunosuppression: what can we learn from severe acute respiratory syndrome? Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2020;38(2):337-342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez Mesa A, Cabrera César E, Martín-Montañez E, et al. Acute lung injury biomarkers in the prediction of COVID-19 severity: total thiol, ferritin and lactate dehydrogenase. Antioxidants. 2021;10(8):1221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pooja S, Francis A, Bid HK, et al. Role of ethnic variations in TNF-α and TNF-β polymorphisms and risk of breast cancer in India. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2011;126(3):739-747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez-Venegas A, Gonz lez-Bonilla C, Borja-Aburto V. Pandemic influenza A/H1N1 virus infection and TNF, LTA, IL1B, IL6, IL8, and CCL polymorphisms in Mexican population: a case-control study. BMC Infect Dis. 2012;12(1):299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reséndiz-Hernández JM, Ambrocio-Ortiz E, Pérez-Rubio G, et al. TNF promoter polymorphisms are associated with genetic susceptibility in COPD secondary to tobacco smoking and biomass burning. Int J Chronic Obstruct Pulm Dis. 2018;13:627-637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solé-Violán J, de Castro Fv, García-Laorden MI, et al. Genetic variability in the severity and outcome of community-acquired pneumonia. Respir Med. 2010;104(3):440-447.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puthothu B, Bierbaum S, Kopp MV, et al. Association of TNF-α with severe respiratory syncytial virus infection and bronchial asthma. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. 2009;20(2):157-163.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>