<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34374951</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2193-8229</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infectious diseases and therapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Dis Ther</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Narrative Review of the Clinical Practicalities of Bamlanivimab and Etesevimab Antibody Therapies for SARS-CoV-2.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><MedlinePgn>1933-1947</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40121-021-00515-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The severity of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) ranges from mild to death, with high morbidity and mortality rates reported amongst a vulnerable subset of patients termed high risk. While vaccines remain the primary option for COVID-19 prevention, neutralizing monoclonal antibodies (mAbs), such as bamlanivimab and etesevimab, have been shown to benefit certain subpopulations after exposure to severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Unlike vaccine-derived immunity that develops over time, administration of neutralizing mAbs is an immediate and passive immunotherapy, with the potential to reduce disease progression, emergency room visits, hospitalizations, and death. Bamlanivimab alone and together with etesevimab hold emergency use authorizations in several countries globally, with countries increasingly transitioning to the use of bamlanivimab and etesevimab together and other authorized mAbs on the basis of their evolving variant landscape, regulatory authorizations, and access to drugs. The current guidelines for the administration of bamlanivimab alone or together with etesevimab are informed by an iterative process of testing and development. Herein the rationale for these guidelines is provided by sharing the learnings that have been gathered throughout the development process of these mAbs. In addition, this review addresses the most common clinical questions received from health care professionals (HCPs) and patients regarding indicated population, dose, use with other medications and vaccines, duration of protection, and variants in clinical practice. As prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 variants can differ by country and state, prescribing HCPs should consider the prevalence of bamlanivimab and etesevimab resistant variants in their area, where data are available, regarding potential efficacy impact when considering treatment options.Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT04427501; NCT04411628; NCT04497987; NCT04634409.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nathan</LastName><ForeName>Ramesh</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Los Robles Health System, Thousand Oaks, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shawa</LastName><ForeName>Imad</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Franciscan Health, 701E County Line Rd, Ste 101, Greenwood, IN, 46143, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De La Torre</LastName><ForeName>Inmaculada</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company, Indianapolis, IN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pustizzi</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company, Indianapolis, IN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haustrup</LastName><ForeName>Natalie</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4516-188X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company, Indianapolis, IN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Dipak R</ForeName><Initials>DR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company, Indianapolis, IN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huhn</LastName><ForeName>Gregory</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ruth M. Rothstein CORE Center, Cook County Health and Hospital System, Chicago, IL, USA. ghuhn@cookcountyhhs.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT04427501</AccessionNumber><AccessionNumber>NCT04411628</AccessionNumber><AccessionNumber>NCT04634409</AccessionNumber><AccessionNumber>NCT04497987</AccessionNumber><AccessionNumber>NCT04427501</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>New Zealand</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Dis Ther</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634499</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2193-6382</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bamlanivimab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Etesevimab</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health care practitioners</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Monoclonal antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34374951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40121-021-00515-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40121-021-00515-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8353431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Guo H, Zhou P, Shi Z-L. Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19(3):141–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-00459-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renn A, Fu Y, Hu X, Hall MD, Simeonov A. Fruitful neutralizing antibody pipeline brings hope to defeat SARS-Cov-2. Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2020;41(11):815–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tips.2020.07.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krammer F. SARS-CoV-2 vaccines in development. Nature. 2020;586(7830):516–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2798-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mello MM, Silverman RD, Omer SB. Ensuring uptake of vaccines against SARS-CoV-2. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(14):1296–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMp2020926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marovich M, Mascola JR, Cohen MS. Monoclonal antibodies for prevention and treatment of COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;324(2):131–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.10245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen P, Nirula A, Heller B, et al. SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody LY-CoV555 in outpatients with Covid-19. N Engl J Med. 2020;384(3):229–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2029849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marston HD, Paules CI, Fauci AS. Monoclonal antibodies for emerging infectious diseases—borrowing from history. N Engl J Med. 2018;378(16):1469–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1802256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen MS, Nirula A, Mulligan MJ, et al. Effect of bamlanivimab vs placebo on incidence of COVID-19 among residents and staff of skilled nursing and assisted living facilities: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2021;326(1):46–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.8828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor PC, Adams AC, Hufford MM, de la Torre I, Winthrop K, Gottlieb RL. Neutralizing monoclonal antibodies for treatment of COVID-19. Nat Rev Immunol. 2021;21(6):382–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41577-021-00542-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eli Lilly and Company. Lilly begins world’s first study of a potential COVID-19 antibody treatment in humans [press release]. June 1, 2020. https://investor.lilly.com/node/43276/pdf . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ClinicalTrials.gov. A study of LY3819253 (LY-CoV555) in participants hospitalized for COVID-19. NCT04411628. 2020. https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/history/NCT04411628 . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baum A, Fulton BO, Wloga E, et al. Antibody cocktail to SARS-CoV-2 spike protein prevents rapid mutational escape seen with individual antibodies. Science. 2020;369(6506):1014–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abd0831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gottlieb RL, Nirula A, Chen P, et al. Effect of bamlanivimab as monotherapy or in combination with etesevimab on viral load in patients with mild to moderate COVID-19: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2021;325(7):632–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2021.0202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Fact Sheet for health care providers: Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) of sotrovimab. 2021. https://www.fda.gov/media/149534/download . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Fact sheet for health care providers: Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) of caririvimab and imdevimab. 2021. https://www.fda.gov/media/143892/download2021 . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dougan M, Nirula M, Azizad M, et al. Bamlanivimab plus etesevimab in mild or moderate COVID-19. N Engl J Med. 2021. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa2102685 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2102685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34260849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8314785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. COVID-19: developing drugs and biological products for treatment or prevention guidance for industry, Updated February 22, 2021. 2020. https://www.fda.gov/media/137926/download . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. People with certain medical conditions. Certain medical condititions and risk for severe COVID-19 illness. Updated November 2, 2020. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/need-extra-precautions/people-with-medical-conditions.html . Accessed 2 Mar 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Fact sheet for health care providers: Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) of bamlanivimab and etesevimab. 2021. https://www.fda.gov/media/145802/download . Accessed 9 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marshall JC, Murthy S, Diaz J, et al. A minimal common outcome measure set for COVID-19 clinical research. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20(8):e192–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30483-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones BE, Brown-Augsburger PL, Corbett KS, et al. The neutralizing antibody, LY-CoV555, protects against SARS-CoV-2 infection in nonhuman primates. Sci Transl Med. 2021;13(593):eabf1906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abf1906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Fact sheet for health care providers: Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) of bamlanivimab. 2020. https://www.fda.gov/media/143603/download . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Medical Agency. EMA issues advice on use of antibody combination (bamlanivimab/etesevimab). March 5, 2021. https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/news/ema-issues-advice-use-antibody-combination-bamlanivimab-etesevimabEMA.CHMP . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Coronavirus (COVID-19) update: FDA authorizes additional monoclonal antibody for treatment of COVID-19. May 26, 2021. https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/coronavirus-covid-19-update-fda-authorizes-additional-monoclonal-antibody-treatment-covid-19 . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson EJ, Walker AJ, Bhaskaran K, et al. Factors associated with COVID-19-related death using OpenSAFELY. Nature. 2020;584(7821):430–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2521-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko JY, Danielson ML, Town M, et al. Risk factors for COVID-19-associated hospitalization: COVID-19-associated hospitalization surveillance network and behavioral risk factor surveillance system. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;72(11):e695–703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa1419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrilli CM, Jones SA, Yang J, et al. Factors associated with hospital admission and critical illness among 5279 people with coronavirus disease 2019 in New York City: prospective cohort study. BMJ. 2020;369:m1966.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan RE, Adab P, Cheng KK. Covid-19: risk factors for severe disease and death. BMJ. 2020;368:m1198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hariyanto TI, Putri C, Situmeang RFV, Kurniawan A. Dementia is a predictor for mortality outcome from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2021;271(2):393–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-020-01205-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwenandar F, Japar KV, Damay V, et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 and cardiovascular system: a narrative review. IJC Heart Vasc. 2020;29: 100557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijcha.2020.100557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Putri C, Hariyanto TI, Hananto JE, et al. Parkinson’s disease may worsen outcomes from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pneumonia in hospitalized patients: a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2021;87:155–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.parkreldis.2021.04.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. science brief: evidence used to update the list of underlying medical conditions that increase a person’s risk of severe illness from COVID-19; Updated May 12, 2021. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/science/science-briefs/underlying-evidence-table.html . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eli Lilly and Company. Can bamlanivimab and etesevimab be used during pregnancy? https://www.lillymedical.com/en-us/answers/can-bamlanivimab-and-etesevimab-be-used-during-pregnancy-137197 . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eli Lilly and Company. What information is available regarding the use of bamlanivimab and etesevimab in pediatric patients? 2021. https://www.lillymedical.com/en-us/answers/what-information-is-available-regarding-the-use-of-bamlanivimab-and-etesevimab-in-pediatric-patients-137194 . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong Y, Mo X, Hu Y, et al. Epidemiology of COVID-19 among children in China. Pediatrics. 2020;145(6): e20200702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2020-0702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu X, Zhang L, Du H, et al. SARS-CoV-2 infection in children. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(17):1663–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2005073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leidman E, Duca LM, Omura JD, Proia K, Stephens JW, Sauber-Schatz EK. COVID-19 trends among persons aged 0–24 years—United States, March 1–December 12, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(3):88–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7003e1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Götzinger F, Santiago-García B, Noguera-Julián A, et al. COVID-19 in children and adolescents in Europe: a multinational, multicentre cohort study. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2020;4(9):653–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30177-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Clinical growth charts; updated June 16, 2017. https://www.cdc.gov/growthcharts/clinical_charts.html . Accessed 10 Mar 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liguoro I, Pilotto C, Bonanni M, et al. SARS-COV-2 infection in children and newborns: a systematic review. Eur J Pediatr. 2020;179(7):1029–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-020-03684-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shekerdemian LS, Mahmood NR, Wolfe KK, et al. Characteristics and outcomes of children with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection admitted to US and Canadian pediatric intensive care units. JAMA Pediatr. 2020;174(9):868–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eli Lilly and Company. Lilly's bamlanivimab and etesevimab together reduced hospitalizations and death in phase 3 trial for early COVID-19 [press release]. March 10, 2021. https://investor.lilly.com/news-releases/news-release-details/lillys-bamlanivimab-and-etesevimab-together-reduced . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of the Assistant Secretary for Preparedeness and Response. Update: Allocation and distribution of COVID-19 therapeutics. April 28, 2021. https://www.healthy.arkansas.gov/images/uploads/pdf/HHS_ASPR_Tx_Allocation_Distro__Stakeholder_Updates_04.28.21_FINAL.pdf . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bariola JR, McCreary EK, Khadem T, et al. Establishing a distribution network for COVID-19 monoclonal antibody therapy across a large health system during a global pandemic. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2021;8:ofab151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofab151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razonable RR, Aloia NCE, Anderson RJ, et al. A framework for outpatient infusion of antispike monoclonal antibodies to high-risk patients with mild-to-moderate coronavirus disease-19: The Mayo Clinic Model. Mayo Clin Proc. 2021;96(5):1250–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mayocp.2021.03.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tulledge-Scheitel S, Bell SJ, Larsen JJ, et al. A mobile unit overcomes the challenges to monoclonal antibody infusion for COVID-19 in skilled care facilities. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2021;69(4):868–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jgs.17090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris AK, Gibson AM, Spencer B, et al. Rapid implementation of a new ambulatory infusion location for patients with COVID-19 to receive monoclonal antibody therapy. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2021;78(13):1166–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ajhp/zxab054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar RN, Wu E-L, Stosor V, et al. Real-world experience of bamlanivimab for COVID-19: a case-control study. Clin Infect Dis. 2021;ciab305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bariola JR, McCreary EK, Wadas RJ, et al. Impact of bamlanivimab monoclonal antibody treatment on hospitalization and mortality among non-hospitalized adults with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2021;8(7):ofab254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofab254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bariola JR, McCreary EK, Wadas RJ, et al. Impact of monoclonal antibody treatment on hospitalization and mortality among non-hospitalized adults with SARS-CoV-2 infection. medRxiv. 2021:03.25.21254322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhand A, Lobo SA, Wolfe K, Feola N, Nabors C. Bamlanivimab for treatment of COVID-19 in solid organ transplant recipients: early single-center experience. Clin Transplant. 2021;35(4): e14245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ctr.14245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webb BJ, Buckel W, Vento T, et al. Real-world effectiveness and tolerability of monoclonal antibodies for ambulatory patients with early COVID-19. medRxiv. 2021.03.15.21253646.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elmeliegy M, Yang DZ, Salama E, Parivar K, Wang DD. Discordance between Child-Pugh and national cancer institute classifications for hepatic dysfunction: implications on dosing recommendations for oncology compounds. J Clin Pharmacol. 2021;61(1):105–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcph.1702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jillella AP, Dainer PM, Kallab AM, Ustun C. Treatment of a patient with end-stage renal disease with rituximab: pharmacokinetic evaluation suggests rituximab is not eliminated by hemodialysis. Am J Hematol. 2002;71(3):219–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ajh.10213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meibohm B, Zhou H. Characterizing the impact of renal impairment on the clinical pharmacology of biologics. J Clin Pharmacol. 2012;52(1 Suppl):54s–62s.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22232754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Understanding how vaccines work. 2018. https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/hcp/conversations/understanding-vacc-work.html . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Interim clinical considerations for use of mRNA COVID-19 vaccines currently authorized in the United States. February 10, 2021. https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/covid-19/info-by-product/clinical-considerations.html . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Interim clinical considerations for use of COVID-19 vaccines currently authorized in the United States. March 5, 2021 https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/covid-19/info-by-product/clinical-considerations.html . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Genomic surveillance for SARS-CoV-2 variants. May 17, 2021. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/variant-surveillance.html . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 variant tracker. 2021. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/cases-updates/variant-proportions.html Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Tracking SARS-CoV-2 variants. May 31, 2021. https://www.who.int/en/activities/tracking-SARS-CoV-2-variants/ . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Toole A, Hill V, Pybus OG, et al. PANGO: lineage assignment in an emerging pandemic as an epidemiological tool. https://cov-lineages.org/lineages.html . Accessed 4 June 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams TC, Burgers WA. SARS-CoV-2 evolution and vaccines: cause for concern? Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(4):333–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00075-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern and variants of interest. 2021. https://www.who.int/en/activities/tracking-SARS-CoV-2-variants/ . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kallewaard N, Heinz BA, Siegel RW, et al., editors. Variant selection, characterization and impact on antibody SARS-CoV-2 neutralization. In: Conference on retroviruses and opportunistic infections (CROI). 2021. https://www.croiconference.org/abstract/variant-selection-characterization-and-impact-on-antibody-sars-cov-2-neutralization/ . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Department of Health and Human Services. Distribution of bamlanivimab/etesevimab paused to Arizona, California, Florida, Indiana, Oregon, and Washington in addition to Illinois and Massachusetts. May 26, 2021. https://www.phe.gov/emergency/events/COVID19/investigation-MCM/Bamlanivimab-etesevimab/Pages/default.aspx . Accessed 15 July 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Planas D, Veyer D, Baidaliuk A, et al. Reduced sensitivity of infectious SARS-CoV-2 variant B.1.617.2 to monoclonal antibodies and sera from convalescent and vaccinated individuals. bioRxiv. 2021. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.26.445838 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2021.05.26.445838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang DT, McCreary EK, Bariola JR, et al. The UPMC OPTIMISE-C19 (OPtimizing Treatment and Impact of Monoclonal antIbodieS through Evaluation for COVID-19) trial: a structured summary of a study protocol for an open-label, pragmatic, comparative effectiveness platform trial with response-adaptive randomization. Trials. 2021;22(1):1–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13063-020-04976-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>