<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34596095</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-6322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in allergy and clinical immunology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 and X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA) - insights from a monogenic antibody deficiency.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><MedlinePgn>525-534</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/ACI.0000000000000792</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW">The clinical outcomes from COVID-19 in monogenic causes of predominant antibody deficiency have pivotal implications for our understanding of the antiviral contribution of humoral immunity. This review summarizes the lessons learned from COVID-19 infection in X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA) due to genetic defects in Bruton's tyrosine kinase (BTK).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS">Key molecular pathways underlying the development of severe COVID-19 are emerging, highlighting the possible contribution of BTK to hyperinflammation. SARS-CoV-2 specific T-cell responses and complement activation appear insufficient to achieve viral clearance in some B-cell deficient individuals. Whilst appearing efficacious in this group, use of convalescent plasma has been recently associated with the evolution of viral escape variants. Early data suggests individuals with XLA can mount a viral-specific T-cell vaccine response, however, the clinical significance of this is still emerging.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUMMARY">In contrast to reports made early in the pandemic, we show XLA patients remain susceptible to severe disease. Persistent infection was common and is likely to carry a significant symptom burden and risk of novel variant evolution. COVID-19 infection in this vulnerable, antibody deficient group due to genetic, therapeutic or disease causes may require prompt and specific intervention for both patient and societal benefit.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2021 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ponsford</LastName><ForeName>Mark J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunodeficiency Centre for Wales, University Hospital for Wales.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Henry Wellcome Building, Division of Infection &amp; Immunity, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shillitoe</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin M J</ForeName><Initials>BMJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Paediatric Immunology, Great North Children's Hospital, Newcastle upon Tyne.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Humphreys</LastName><ForeName>Ian R</ForeName><Initials>IR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Henry Wellcome Building, Division of Infection &amp; Immunity, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Systems Immunity Research Institute, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gennery</LastName><ForeName>Andrew R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Paediatric Immunology, Great North Children's Hospital, Newcastle upon Tyne.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Translational and Clinical Research Institute, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jolles</LastName><ForeName>Stephen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunodeficiency Centre for Wales, University Hospital for Wales.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100936359</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1473-6322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>EC 2.7.10.2</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000077329">Agammaglobulinaemia Tyrosine Kinase</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C537409">Bruton type agammaglobulinemia</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077329" MajorTopicYN="N">Agammaglobulinaemia Tyrosine Kinase</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="Y">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000361" MajorTopicYN="N">Agammaglobulinemia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="Y">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019143" MajorTopicYN="N">Evolution, Molecular</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D040181" MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic Diseases, X-Linked</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="Y">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="N">pathogenicity</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012720" MajorTopicYN="N">Severity of Illness Index</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34596095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ACI.0000000000000792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00130832-900000000-98971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Meyts I, Bucciol G, Quinti I, et al. Coronavirus Disease 2019 in patients with inborn errors of immunity: an international study. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2021; 147:520–531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shields AM, Burns SO, Savic S, et al. COVID-19 in patients with primary and secondary immunodeficiency: The United Kingdom experience. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2021; 147:870-875.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bousfiha A, Jeddane L, Picard C, et al. Human inborn errors of immunity: 2019 update of the IUIS phenotypical classification. J Clin Immunol 2020; 40:66–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q, Bastard P, Liu Z, et al. Inborn errors of type I IFN immunity in patients with life-threatening COVID-19. Science 2020; 370:eabd4570.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastard P, Rosen LB, Zhang Q, et al. Autoantibodies against type I IFNs in patients with life-threatening COVID-19. Science 2020; 370:eabd4585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinti I, Lougaris V, Milito C, et al. A possible role for B cells in COVID-19? Lesson from patients with agammaglobulinemia. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2020; 146:211-213.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponsford MJ, Price C, Farewell D, et al. Increased respiratory viral detection and symptom burden among patients with primary antibody deficiency: results from the BIPAD study. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract 2021; 9:735–744.e6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shillitoe BMJ, Ponsford M, Slatter MA, et al. Haematopoietic stem cell transplant for norovirus-induced intestinal failure in X-linked agammaglobulinemia. J Clin Immunol 2021; 41:1574–1581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sperlich JM, Grimbacher B, Workman S, et al. Respiratory infections and antibiotic usage in common variable immunodeficiency. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract 2018; 6:159-168.e3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kainulainen L, Vuorinen T, Rantakokko-Jalava K, et al. Recurrent and persistent respiratory tract viral infections in patients with primary hypogammaglobulinemia. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2010; 126:120–126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linnemann CC Jr, May DB, Schubert WK, et al. Fatal viral encephalitis in children with X-linked hypogammaglobulinemia. Am J Dis Child 1973; 126:100–103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilfert CM, Buckley RH, Mohanakumar T, et al. Persistent and fatal central-nervous-system ECHOvirus infections in patients with agammaglobulinemia. N Engl J Med 1977; 296:1485–1489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sochorová K, Horváth R, Rozková D, et al. Impaired Toll-like receptor 8-mediated IL-6 and TNF-alpha production in antigen-presenting cells from patients with X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Blood 2007; 109:2553–2556.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahmahmoodi S, Mamishi S, Aghamohammadi A, et al. Vaccine-associated paralytic poliomyelitis in immunodeficient children, Iran. Emerg Infect Dis 2010; 16:1133–1136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vabret N, Britton GJ, Gruber C, et al. Immunology of COVID-19: current state of the science. Immunity 2020; 52:910–941.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Q, Bao L, Mao H, et al. Development of an inactivated vaccine candidate for SARS-CoV-2. Science 2020; 369:77–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Libster R, Pérez Marc G, Wappner D, et al. Early High-Titer Plasma Therapy to Prevent Severe Covid-19 in Older Adults. N Engl J Med 2021; 384:610–618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton FW, Lee T, Arnold DT, et al. Is convalescent plasma futile in COVID-19? A Bayesian re-analysis of the RECOVERY randomized controlled trial. Int J Infect Dis 2021; 109:114–117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinreich DM, Sivapalasingam S, Norton T, et al. REGN-COV2, a neutralizing antibody cocktail, in outpatients with covid-19. N Engl J Med 2021; 384:238–251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horby PW, Mafham M, Peto L, et al. Casirivimab and imdevimab in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): a randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial. medRxiv 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brunner C, Müller B, Wirth T. Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase is involved in innate and adaptive immunity. Histol Histopathol 2005; 20:945–955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bao Y, Zheng J, Han C, et al. Tyrosine kinase Btk is required for NK cell activation. J Biol Chem 2012; 287:23769–23778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murthy P, Durco F, Miller-Ocuin JL, et al. The NLRP3 inflammasome and bruton's tyrosine kinase in platelets co-regulate platelet activation, aggregation, and in vitro thrombus formation. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 2017; 483:230–236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soresina A, Moratto D, Chiarini M, et al. Two X-linked agammaglobulinemia patients develop pneumonia as COVID-19 manifestation but recover. Pediatr Allergy Immunol 2020; 31:565–569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham-Rundles C. Human B cell defects in perspective. Immunol Res 2012; 54:227–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lougaris V, Baronio M, Vitali M, et al. Bruton tyrosine kinase mediates TLR9-dependent human dendritic cell activation. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2014; 133:1644-1650.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marron TU, Martinez-Gallo M, Yu JE, et al. Toll-like receptor 4-, 7-, and 8-activated myeloid cells from patients with X-linked agammaglobulinemia produce enhanced inflammatory cytokines. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2012; 129:184-190.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roschewski M, Lionakis MS, Sharman JP, et al. Inhibition of Bruton tyrosine kinase in patients with severe COVID-19. Sci Immunol 2020; 5:eabd0110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abani O, Abbas A, Abbas F, et al. Tocilizumab in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): a randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial. Lancet 2021; 397:1637–1645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stack M, Sacco K, Castagnoli R, et al. BTK inhibitors for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2): a systematic review. Clin Immunol 2021; 230:108816.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin H, Reed JC, Liu STH, et al. Three patients with X-linked agammaglobulinemia hospitalized for COVID-19 improved with convalescent plasma. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract 2020; 8:3594-3596.e3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh SY, Bassett J, Hoodless EJ, Walshaw M. Possible COVID-19 reinfection in a patient with X-linked agammaglobulinaemia. BMJ Case Rep 2021; 14:e240765.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iaboni A, Wong N, Betschel SD. A patient with X-Linked agammaglobulinemia and COVID-19 infection treated with remdesivir and convalescent plasma. J Clin Immunol 2021; 41:8–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buckland MS, Galloway JB, Fhogartaigh CN, et al. Treatment of COVID-19 with remdesivir in the absence of humoral immunity: a case report. Nat Commun 2020; 11:6385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zelek WM, Cole J, Ponsford MJ, et al. Complement inhibition with the C5 Blocker LFG316 in severe COVID-19. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2020; 202:1304–1308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verity R, Okell LC, Dorigatti I, et al. Estimates of the severity of coronavirus disease 2019: a model-based analysis. Lancet Infect Dis 2020; 20:669–677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cevik M, Tate M, Lloyd O, et al. SARS-CoV-2, SARS-CoV, and MERS-CoV viral load dynamics, duration of viral shedding, and infectiousness: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Microbe 2021; 2:e13–e22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hueso T, Pouderoux C, Péré H, et al. Convalescent plasma therapy for B-cell-depleted patients with protracted COVID-19. Blood 2020; 136:2290–2295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aviv R, Weber A, Anzum T, et al. Prolonged COVID-19 Disease in a Patient with Rheumatoid Arthritis on Rituximab Therapy. J Infect Dis 2021; 224:557–559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kemp SA, Collier DA, Datir RP, et al. SARS-CoV-2 evolution during treatment of chronic infection. Nature 2021; 592:277–282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson MK, Hamilton F, Hutchings S, et al. Chronic SARS-CoV-2 infection and viral evolution in a hypogammaglobulinaemic individual. medRxiv 2021; 2021.05.31.21257591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagin D, Freund T, Navon M, et al. Immunogenicity of pfizer-biontech COVID-19 vaccine in patients with inborn errors of immunity. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2021; 148:739–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salinas AF, Mortari EP, Terreri S, et al. SARS-CoV-2 vaccine induced atypical immune responses in antibody defects: everybody does their best. medRxiv 2021; 2021.06.24.21259130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Wu Y, Lam K-T, Lee PP-W, Tu W, Lau Y-L. Dendritic and T Cell Response to Influenza is Normal in the Patients with X-Linked Agammaglobulinemia. J Clin Immunol 2012; 32:421–429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel SY, Carbone J, Jolles S. The expanding field of secondary antibody deficiency: Causes, diagnosis, and management. Front Immunol 2019; 10:33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devassikutty FM, Jain A, Edavazhippurath A, et al. X-Linked Agammaglobulinemia and COVID-19: Two Case Reports and Review of Literature. Pediatr Allergy Immunol Pulmonol 2021; 34:115–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milošević I, Jovanović J, Stevanović O. Atypical course of COVID-19 in patient with Bruton agammaglobulinemia. J Infect Dev Countries 2020; 14:1248–1251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcus N, Frizinsky S, Hagin D, et al. Minor clinical impact of COVID-19 pandemic on patients with primary immunodeficiency in Israel. Front Immunol 2021; 11:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guetl K, Moazedi-Fuerst F, Rosskopf K, et al. SARS-CoV-2 positive virus culture 7 weeks after onset of COVID-19 in an immunocompromised patient suffering from X chromosome-linked agammaglobulinemia. J Infect 2021; 82:414–451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mira E, Yarce OA, Ortega C, et al. Rapid recovery of a SARS-CoV-2-infected X-linked agammaglobulinemia patient after infusion of COVID-19 convalescent plasma. J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract 2020; 8:2793–2795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hovey JG, Tolbert D, Howell D. Burton's Agammaglobulinemia and COVID-19. Cureus 2020; 12:e11701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almontasheri A, Al-Husayni F, Alsuraihi AK, et al. The clinical course of COVID-19 pneumonia in a 19-year-old man on intravenous immunoglobulin replacement therapy for X-linked agammaglobulinemia. Am J Case Rep 2021; 22:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber ANR, Bittner Z, Liu X, et al. Bruton's tyrosine kinase: an emerging key player in innate immunity. Front Immunol 2017; 8:1454.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>