<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2019//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_190101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="In-Process" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34608598</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1572-994X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>57</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virus genes</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virus Genes</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sensitivity of two SARS-CoV-2 variants with spike protein mutations to neutralising antibodies.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><MedlinePgn>502-509</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11262-021-01871-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>SARS-CoV-2 infections elicit a humoral immune response capable of neutralising the virus. However, multiple variants have emerged with mutations in the spike protein amongst others, the key target of neutralising antibodies. We evaluated the neutralising efficacy of 89 serum samples from patients, infected with SARS-CoV-2 in the beginning of 2020, against two virus variants isolated from acutely infected patients and harbouring spike protein mutations. One isolate was assigned to lineage B.1.351 (MUC-IMB-B.1.351) whilst the other (MUC-484) was isolated from an immunocompromised patient, sharing some but not all mutations with B.1.351 and representing a transitional variant. Both variants showed a significant reduction in neutralisation sensitivity compared to wild-type SARS-CoV-2 with MUC-IMB-B.1.351 being almost completely resistant to neutralisation. The observed reduction in neutralising activity of wild-type-specific antibodies against both variants suggests that individual mutations in the spike protein are sufficient to confer a potent escape from the humoral immune response. In addition, the effect of escape mutations seems to accumulate, so that more heavily mutated variants show a greater loss of sensitivity to neutralisation up to complete insensitivity as observed for MUC-IMB-B.1.351. From a clinical point of view, this might affect the efficacy of (monoclonal) antibody treatment of patients with prolonged infections as well as patients infected with variants other than the donor. At the same, this could also negatively influence the efficacy of current vaccines (as they are based on wild-type spike protein) emphasising the need to thoroughly surveil the emergence and distribution of variants and adapt vaccines and therapeutics accordingly.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2021. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Müller</LastName><ForeName>Katharina</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bundeswehr Institute of Microbiology, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Girl</LastName><ForeName>Philipp</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1370-4114</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bundeswehr Institute of Microbiology, Munich, Germany. philippgirl@bundeswehr.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner site Munich, Munich, Germany. philippgirl@bundeswehr.org.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giebl</LastName><ForeName>Andreas</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, Institute for Transfusion Medicine and Haemostasis, University of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gruetzner</LastName><ForeName>Stefanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, Institute for Transfusion Medicine and Haemostasis, University of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Antwerpen</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bundeswehr Institute of Microbiology, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khatamzas</LastName><ForeName>Elham</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine III, LMU Hospital Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wölfel</LastName><ForeName>Roman</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bundeswehr Institute of Microbiology, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>von Buttlar</LastName><ForeName>Heiner</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bundeswehr Institute of Microbiology, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner site Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Virus Genes</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8803967</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0920-8569</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">B.1.351</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune escape</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mutation E484K</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neutralising antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Variants of concern</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34608598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11262-021-01871-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11262-021-01871-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8489549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Du L (2021) SARS-CoV-2 spike protein: a key target for eliciting persistent neutralizing antibodies. Sig Transduct Target Ther 6:95. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-021-00523-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-021-00523-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaebler C, Wang Z, Lorenzi JCC, Muecksch F, Finkin S, Tokuyama M, Cho A, Jankovic M, Schaefer-Babajew D, Oliveira TY, Cipolla M, Viant C, Barnes CO, Bram Y, Breton G, Hägglöf T, Mendoza P, Hurley A, Turroja M, Gordon K, Millard KG, Ramos V, Schmidt F, Weisblum Y, Jha D, Tankelevich M, Martinez-Delgado G, Yee J, Patel R, Dizon J, Unson-O’Brien C, Shimeliovich I, Robbiani DF, Zhao Z, Gazumyan A, Schwartz RE, Hatziioannou T, Bjorkman PJ, Mehandru S, Bieniasz PD, Caskey M, Nussenzweig MC (2021) Evolution of antibody immunity to SARS-CoV-2. Nature 591:639–644. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03207-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03207-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8221082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey WT, Carabelli AM, Jackson B, Gupta RK, Thomson EC, Harrison EM, Ludden C, Reeve R, Rambaut A, COVID-19 Genomics UK (COG-UK) Consortium, Peacock SJ, Robertson DL (2021) SARS-CoV-2 variants, spike mutations and immune escape. Nat Rev Microbiol 19:409–424. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-021-00573-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-021-00573-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller K, Girl P, Giebl A, von Buttlar H, Dobler G, Bugert JJ, Gruetzner S, Wölfel R (2021) Emerging SARS-CoV-2 variant B.1.1.7 reduces neutralisation activity of antibodies against wild-type SARS-CoV-2. J Clin Virol 142:104912. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2021.104912</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2021.104912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34298379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8282447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatamzas E, Rehn A, Muenchhoff M, Hellmuth J, Gaitzsch E, Weiglein T, Georgi E, Scherer C, Stecher S, Weigert O, Girl P, Zange S, Keppler OT, Stemmler J, Bergwelt-Baildon M von, Wölfel R, Antwerpen M (2021) Emergence of multiple SARS-CoV-2 mutations in an immunocompromised host. medRxiv 2021.01.10.20248871. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.01.10.20248871</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wölfel R, Corman VM, Guggemos W, Seilmaier M, Zange S, Müller MA, Niemeyer D, Jones TC, Vollmar P, Rothe C, Hoelscher M, Bleicker T, Brünink S, Schneider J, Ehmann R, Zwirglmaier K, Drosten C, Wendtner C (2020) Virological assessment of hospitalized patients with COVID-2019. Nature 581:465–469. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2196-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2196-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32235945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">32235945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) (2021) Tracking SARS-CoV-2 variants. https://www.who.int/activities/tracking-SARS-CoV-2-variants . Accessed 26 Jul 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegally H, Wilkinson E, Giovanetti M, Iranzadeh A, Fonseca V, Giandhari J, Doolabh D, Pillay S, San EJ, Msomi N, Mlisana K, von Gottberg A, Walaza S, Allam M, Ismail A, Mohale T, Glass AJ, Engelbrecht S, Van Zyl G, Preiser W, Petruccione F, Sigal A, Hardie D, Marais G, Hsiao N, Korsman S, Davies M-A, Tyers L, Mudau I, York D, Maslo C, Goedhals D, Abrahams S, Laguda-Akingba O, Alisoltani-Dehkordi A, Godzik A, Wibmer CK, Sewell BT, Lourenço J, Alcantara LCJ, Kosakovsky Pond SL, Weaver S, Martin D, Lessells RJ, Bhiman JN, Williamson C, de Oliveira T (2021) Detection of a SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern in South Africa. Nature 592:438–443. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03402-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03402-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33690265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jangra S, Ye C, Rathnasinghe R, Stadlbauer D, Alshammary H, Amoako AA, Awawda MH, Beach KF, Bermúdez-González MC, Chernet RL, Eaker LQ, Ferreri ED, Floda DL, Gleason CR, Kleiner G, Jurczyszak D, Matthews JC, Mendez WA, Mulder LCF, Russo KT, Salimbangon A-BT, Saksena M, Shin AS, Sominsky LA, Srivastava K, Krammer F, Simon V, Martinez-Sobrido L, García-Sastre A, Schotsaert M (2021) SARS-CoV-2 spike E484K mutation reduces antibody neutralisation. The Lancet Microbe 2:e283–e284. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00068-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00068-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33846703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8026167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou D, Dejnirattisai W, Supasa P, Liu C, Mentzer AJ, Ginn HM, Zhao Y, Duyvesteyn HME, Tuekprakhon A, Nutalai R, Wang B, Paesen GC, Lopez-Camacho C, Slon-Campos J, Hallis B, Coombes N, Bewley K, Charlton S, Walter TS, Skelly D, Lumley SF, Dold C, Levin R, Dong T, Pollard AJ, Knight JC, Crook D, Lambe T, Clutterbuck E, Bibi S, Flaxman A, Bittaye M, Belij-Rammerstorfer S, Gilbert S, James W, Carroll MW, Klenerman P, Barnes E, Dunachie SJ, Fry EE, Mongkolsapaya J, Ren J, Stuart DI, Screaton GR (2021) Evidence of escape of SARS-CoV-2 variant B.1.351 from natural and vaccine-induced sera. Cell 184:2348-2361.e6. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.037</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33730597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7901269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NG, Abbott S, Barnard RC, Jarvis CI, Kucharski AJ, Munday J, Pearson CAB, Russell TW, Tully DC, Washburne AD, Wenseleers T, Gimma A, Waites W, Wong KL, Zandvoort K van, Silverman JD, Group CC-19 W, Diaz-Ordaz K, Keogh R, Eggo RM, Funk S, Jit M, Atkins KE, Edmunds WJ (2021) Estimated transmissibility and severity of novel SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern 202012/01 in England. medRxiv 2020.12.24.20248822 . https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.24.20248822</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration (2021) Fact sheet for health care providers emergency use authorization (EUA) of Bamlanivimab</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Planas D, Bruel T, Grzelak L, Guivel-Benhassine F, Staropoli I, Porrot F, Planchais C, Buchrieser J, Rajah MM, Bishop E, Albert M, Donati F, Prot M, Behillil S, Enouf V, Maquart M, Smati-Lafarge M, Varon E, Schortgen F, Yahyaoui L, Gonzalez M, De Sèze J, Péré H, Veyer D, Sève A, Simon-Lorière E, Fafi-Kremer S, Stefic K, Mouquet H, Hocqueloux L, van der Werf S, Prazuck T, Schwartz O (2021) Sensitivity of infectious SARS-CoV-2 B.1.1.7 and B.1.351 variants to neutralizing antibodies. Nat Med 27:917–924. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-021-01318-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01318-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33772244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korber B, Fischer WM, Gnanakaran S, Yoon H, Theiler J, Abfalterer W, Hengartner N, Giorgi EE, Bhattacharya T, Foley B, Hastie KM, Parker MD, Partridge DG, Evans CM, Freeman TM, de Silva TI, Angyal A, Brown RL, Carrilero L, Green LR, Groves DC, Johnson KJ, Keeley AJ, Lindsey BB, Parsons PJ, Raza M, Rowland-Jones S, Smith N, Tucker RM, Wang D, Wyles MD, McDanal C, Perez LG, Tang H, Moon-Walker A, Whelan SP, LaBranche CC, Saphire EO, Montefiori DC (2020) Tracking changes in SARS-CoV-2 spike: evidence that D614G increases infectivity of the COVID-19 virus. Cell 182:812-827.e19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2020.06.043</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.06.043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32697968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7332439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul-Ehrlich-Institut—News—Recommendation of the Paul-Ehrlich-Institut for the collection and manufacture of COVID-19 convalescent plasma. https://www.pei.de/EN/newsroom/hp-news/2020/200407-recommendation-pei-covid-19-convalescent-plasma.html;jsessionid=75FE2CC97FB1AC74E8529A023B965614.intranet241 . Accessed 15 Mar 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>(2021) CD8 T cells and antibodies drive SARS-CoV-2 evolution in chronic infection. https://www.researchsquare.com . Accessed 17 Sep 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou J, Zhu LJ (2019) trackViewer: a bioconductor package for interactive and integrative visualization of multi-omics data. Nature Methods. https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-019-0430-y?proof=t . Accessed 17 Sep 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haselmann V, Özçürümez MK, Klawonn F, Ast V, Gerhards C, Eichner R, Costina V, Dobler G, Geilenkeuser W-J, Wölfel R, Neumaier M (2020) Results of the first pilot external quality assessment (EQA) scheme for anti-SARS-CoV2-antibody testing. Clin Chem Lab Med. https://doi.org/10.1515/cclm-2020-1183</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/cclm-2020-1183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S-Y, Kung Y-A, Huang P-N, Chang S-Y, Gong Y-N, Han Y-J, Chiang H-J, Liu K-T, Lee K-M, Chang C-Y, Chang C-C, Huang C-G, Shih S-R (2021) Stability of SARS-CoV-2 spike G614 variant surpasses that of the D614 variant after cold storage. mSphere 6:e00104-21. https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00104-21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00104-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33789940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8546686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozono S, Zhang Y, Ode H, Sano K, Tan TS, Imai K, Miyoshi K, Kishigami S, Ueno T, Iwatani Y, Suzuki T, Tokunaga K (2021) SARS-CoV-2 D614G spike mutation increases entry efficiency with enhanced ACE2-binding affinity. Nat Commun 12:848. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21118-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-21118-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33558493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7870668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Nie J, Wu J, Zhang L, Ding R, Wang H, Zhang Y, Li T, Liu S, Zhang M, Zhao C, Liu H, Nie L, Qin H, Wang M, Lu Q, Li X, Liu J, Liang H, Shi Y, Shen Y, Xie L, Zhang L, Qu X, Xu W, Huang W, Wang Y (2021) SARS-CoV-2 501Y.V2 variants lack higher infectivity but do have immune escape. Cell 184:2362-2371.e9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.02.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33735608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7901273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gan HH, Twaddle A, Marchand B, Gunsalus KC (2021) Structural modeling of the SARS-CoV-2 spike/human ACE2 complex interface can identify high-affinity variants associated with increased transmissibility. J Mol Biol 433:167051. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2021.167051</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2021.167051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33992693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8118711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Wang P, Nair MS, Yu J, Rapp M, Wang Q, Luo Y, Chan JF-W, Sahi V, Figueroa A, Guo XV, Cerutti G, Bimela J, Gorman J, Zhou T, Chen Z, Yuen K-Y, Kwong PD, Sodroski JG, Yin MT, Sheng Z, Huang Y, Shapiro L, Ho DD (2020) Potent neutralizing antibodies against multiple epitopes on SARS-CoV-2 spike. Nature 584:450–456. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2571-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2571-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32698192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCallum M, De Marco A, Lempp FA, Tortorici MA, Pinto D, Walls AC, Beltramello M, Chen A, Liu Z, Zatta F, Zepeda S, di Iulio J, Bowen JE, Montiel-Ruiz M, Zhou J, Rosen LE, Bianchi S, Guarino B, Fregni CS, Abdelnabi R, Foo S-YC, Rothlauf PW, Bloyet L-M, Benigni F, Cameroni E, Neyts J, Riva A, Snell G, Telenti A, Whelan SPJ, Virgin HW, Corti D, Pizzuto MS, Veesler D (2021) N-terminal domain antigenic mapping reveals a site of vulnerability for SARS-CoV-2. Cell 184:2332-2347.e16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33761326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7962585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colson P, Devaux CA, Lagier J-C, Gautret P, Raoult D (2021) A possible role of remdesivir and plasma therapy in the selective sweep and emergence of new SARS-CoV-2 variants. J Clin Med 10:3276. https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm10153276</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm10153276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">8348317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisblum Y, Schmidt F, Zhang F, DaSilva J, Poston D, Lorenzi JC, Muecksch F, Rutkowska M, Hoffmann H-H, Michailidis E, Gaebler C, Agudelo M, Cho A, Wang Z, Gazumyan A, Cipolla M, Luchsinger L, Hillyer CD, Caskey M, Robbiani DF, Rice CM, Nussenzweig MC, Hatziioannou T, Bieniasz PD (2020) Escape from neutralizing antibodies by SARS-CoV-2 spike protein variants. eLife 9:e61312. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.61312</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.61312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33112236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmcid">7723407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>